hi Merry Christmas for those who
celebrate this video releases on
Christmas a worst time to upload but
here we are anyway I'm making this video
because I have some corrections to make
to a video that I released earlier this
month that video is on SAA use for
cardiovascular disease I didn't do a
very good job and I thought this would
be a good opportunity to enunciate what
I got wrong acknowledge how intelligent
the physionic community can be and to do
the work over I'm referring to this
video which I had a ton of fun in making
the thumbnail but uh within that video I
explained the data coming from a meta
analysis looking at 16 studies on sauna
and different metrics of cardiovascular
fitness in the end it showed that sauna
reduces blood pressure and increases
something called ejection fraction and
because I like to hang out in the
comments for the first 12 to 24 hours of
a video for feedback and to control mean
people I ran across several comments
critiquing my work and upon reflection I
think they made some excellent points
that I think should be fixed now to be
clear I've already added an amendment to
that video weeks ago but I'd like to
highlight some points to make a better
conclusion including the critique that I
received the first comment was this one
what is pointed out correctly by PB is
that some of these positive results of
sauna could be due to vasod dilation
that occurs from heat which would reduce
blood pressure and also affect ejection
fraction okay so what does that all mean
visually your blood pressure is
dependent on two main things one the
amount of fluid so volume in your
arteries and two how open or closed your
arteries are if they're closed and tight
that increases blood pressure heat
however like that from sauna opens the
arteries it's called Vas the dilation
this in turn reduces blood pressure this
would explain the drop in blood pressure
that I showed in the data second this
drop in blood pressure also applies to
this area of the heart the aorta if
pressure in the aorta is high the left
ventricle of the heart here requires
more strength to push the blood into the
aorta which would leave more residual
blood in The ventricle as not all of it
can overcome the heightened pressure in
the a aorta however if you drop the
pressure in the aorta the same ventricle
muscles can push just as hard and would
be pushing against less resistance
thereby allowing more blood to move from
The ventricle to the aorta and less
would be found in The ventricle this is
captured by a measure called ejection
fraction and since we already saw blood
pressure drop we would expect ejection
fraction to possibly improve as well
okay so why does this matter well it
matters because short-term changes in he
hemo hemo
hemodynamics what I just explained about
blood flow doesn't necessarily mean
these changes will remain long term my
mistake was to only show the short-term
changes which don't inform on if a
person continues to experience these
benefits hours or days or weeks after
sauna use I should have shown more
convincing data
especially long-term data considering
the data that I showed on blood pressure
was readings taken immediately after
sauna which would be heavily influenced
by the mechanisms that I just described
so let me address this Fair critique and
set the story straight before moving on
to the next critique that same analysis
did show long-term data over several
weeks like this that still indicates a
long-term blood pressure lowering effect
at least after two and four weeks as the
3-we studies were too few and too small
to indicate one way or another in
addition the ejection fraction data was
long-term as presented in the previous
video but as I mentioned in the initial
video there's more evidence especially
long-term data indicating saa's benefit
but let's address another wonderful
Point by another in the physic Community
before we touch on that here's the
second point point the reason I like
this so much is because it could be that
SAA itself is only a bystander as many
saunas are located in gyms and more
physically active people could be using
sauna causing the real effect to come
from physical activity and not sauna use
so as I pointed out in my response some
studies were randomized meaning
physically active and non-physically
active people were had an equ chance of
being in the Sonic condition beyond that
these are intervention studies so the
idea is that the researchers recruit
people who do not already use sauna and
simply add sauna to their daily lives
for the study so the only variable that
changes is sauna use there's still some
inherent weaknesses of sauna studies in
that creating an adequate control group
is tough to do I think a great one to
compare against would be a similar
individuals who do a similar amount of
physical activity to distinguish the
direct additive effect of sauna assuming
there is one anyway let's address both
points simultaneously long-term data
from studies like this indicates sauna
use over 15 years reduces risk of
cardiovascular disease death
substantially and that remains true even
when accounting for physical activity
and another large confounder socio e
economic status so overall I think I
could have done a better job in my
initial presentation but I think this
seriously highlights that a I'm human
and regardless of my education I should
be held to a standard with Fair wellth
thought out critique just to be clear if
you're one of those people that just
says BS that's not what I'm talking
about and B likely more interesting to
you the overall message about sauna use
remains it is still true that sauna is a
benefit in combating cardiovascular
disease I covered several effective
sauna protocols for the physionic
Insiders pulled from multiple studies
but I also expect to release more on the
intricacies of sauna especially in
relation to exercise other outcomes
Beyond heart health and possibly cold
therapy in the future anyway if you want
to check out the original video with
more details it's here and otherwise
thanks for being a member of physionic
means a lot and I hope you have a
wonderful New Year
[Music]